If an N times N square matrix has
N distinct egienvalues, then it is diagonalizable
Which of the following answers is correct for this statement.
A, true. B, false. C, it depends. Or D, I don't know.
The correct answer is A
To understand why this is the correct answer, let
us take a look at Eigenvalues and Eigenvectors
Let's consider a generic matrix A of size N times N, with
eigenvalues lambda 1, lambda 2 all the way up to lambda N.
Let lambda I be a generic eigenvalue of A.
V I is the eigenvector corresponding tolambda I
so lambda I determines how V I stretches after
applying the transformation A.
Now consider a different eigenvalue lambda J
Where lambda J and lambda I are distinct
then let V J be the eigenvector corresponding to lambda J
Eigenvectors of two different eigenvalues
must be linearly independent.
One eigenvector cannot be associated to
two different eigenvalues, because it cannot
be stretched in two different ways.