If an N times N square matrix has
N distinct eigenvalues, then it is diagonalizable
Which of the following answers is correct for this statement.
Option A , true. B, false. C, it depends. Or D, I don't know.
The correct answer is A
To understand why this is the correct answer, let
us take a look at Eigenvalues and Eigenvectors
Let's consider a generic matrix A of size N times N, with
eigenvalues lambda 1, lambda 2 all the way up to lambda N.
Let lambda I be a generic eigenvalue of A.
V I is the eigenvector corresponding tolambda I
so lambda I determines how V I stretches after
applying the transformation A.
Now consider a different eigenvalue lambda J
Where lambda J and lambda I are distinct
then let V J be the eigenvector corresponding to lambda J
Eigenvectors of two different eigenvalues
must be linearly independent.
One eigenvector cannot be associated to
two different eigenvalues, because it cannot
be stretched in two different ways.
Let's go back to the original question:
If an N times N square matrix has N different eigenvalues
is it diagonalizable?